A Guide to the WRVA Radio Collection, 1925-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series XI: Sound Recordings, 1929-1995, 630 compact discs. Duration: 317 hr., 40 min., 38 sec.
  - Byrd, Harry Flood, Senator Harry F. Byrd, 30 August 1958, (WRVA - 525); 1 compact disc. Duration: 14 min., 32 sec.
    Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr., discusses the recent congressional session, commenting on the deterioration of fiscal sanity, reckless expenditures, and federal debt. He attacks the recent decisions of the United States Supreme Court under the leadership of Chief Justice Earl Warren as destroying states' rights, local authority, and individual rights. He criticizes the Warren Court for deciding the desegregation case on a sociological basis rather than a legal one, and promises to fight the decision by every legal means possible.
  - Byrd, Harry Flood, Speech at the Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, 26 June 1952, (WRVA - 123-123A); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 2 sec.
    Recording of speech of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., to the 19th session of the Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. During the speech, Byrd laments the increasing power of the federal government and executive branch. He praises the free enterprise system and warns of the dangers of high taxation and over spending.
  - Byrd, Harry Flood, Speech Before the Ruritan Club, 21 January 1957, (WRVA - 178); 1 compact disc. Duration: 45 min., 42 sec.
    Speech, 21 January 1957, by Senator Harry F. Byrd (1887-1966) before the Ruritan Club in Richmond, Virginia. He is introduced by Lieutenant Governor Allie Edwards Stokes Stephens (1900-1973). Byrd speaks about the centralization of power by the federal government, government spending, inflation, federal deficits, foreign aid waste, the need to keep the military strong and to fight Communism, his work on the Senate Finance Committee, the loss of states' rights, federal money going to public schools, and the recent Supreme Court decision on school integration.
  - Byrd, Harry Flood, Speech Before the Richmond Traffic Club, Hotel John Marshall, 20 February 1961, (WRVA - 227); 1 compact disc. Duration: 53 min., 15 sec.
    Speech, 20 February 1961, by Senator Harry F. Byrd before the Richmond Traffic Club at the Hotel John Marshall. Topics of the speech include the first thirty days of the Kennedy Administration, opposition to the Democratic platform by Southern senators, Senate committee chairmanships, Kennedy's appointments and legislative proposals, Byrd's relationship with past presidents, including Roosevelt, Truman, and Eisenhower, the national debt, welfare, foreign aid, and the gold standard. Byrd also provides the audience with his definition of a conservative.
  - Calling All Cooks, 1949-1954, (WRVA - 41-53); 13 compact discs. Duration: 12 hr., 9 min., 37 sec.
    These recordings consist of the half-hour broadcasts of the Calling All Cooks quiz program and cover each weekly broadcast from 29 October 1949 to 25 March 1950, and then intermittent broadcasts from 3 March 1951 to 13 February 1954, at the WRVA Theater and John Marshall High School in Richmond. The Master of Ceremonies of the show is George Passage, and the announcer is Carl Stutz. Eight women compete on two teams of four as the Cooks and the Bakers, alternately coming on stage and answering cooking and food related questions in order to win prizes provided by the sponsors. Each prize selection is punctuated with a scripted advertisement for the product read by Carl Stutz. At the mid-point of the program, Calling All Cooks Home Economist Harriet Allen provides cooking tips in the Norge kitchen stage set, while bantering back and forth with George Passage.
  - Calling All Cooks Anniversary Program, 8 November 1950, (WRVA - 54); 1 compact disc. Duration: 29 min., 15 sec.
    This recording consists of one half hour episode of Calling All Cooks, which aired during WRVA's week-long celebration of its 25th anniversary. Broadcast live from the WRVA Theater in Richmond, the Master of Ceremonies of the show is George Passage, and the announcer is Carl Stutz. As with the regular program, eight women compete on two teams of four as the Cooks and the Bakers, alternately coming on stage and answering questions in order to win prizes provided by the sponsors. In this instance, however, the questions are all related to either WRVA's 25th anniversary or anniversaries in general. Each prize selection is punctuated with a scripted advertisement for the product read by Carl Stutz. At the mid-point of the program, Calling All Cooks Home Economist Harriett Allen discusses cooking trivia from the Norge kitchen stage set, while bantering back and forth with George Passage.
  - Capitol Airlines Crash Coverage, 18-19 January 1960, (WRVA - 238); 1 compact disc. Duration: 24 min., 14 sec.
    Coverage, 18-19 January 1960, of the crash of a Capitol Airlines jet thirty-five miles southeast of Richmond in Charles City County, Virginia near the small town of Holdcroft. Harry Monroe of WRVA reports from the scene shortly after the crash. Jack Clements also reports from WRVA studios. Included are eyewitness accounts. Names of some of the victims are read on air, and there is speculation by Clements and Monroe on the cause of the crash. The jet, a Vickers Viscount Turboprop, went down at night in a wooded area, enroute from Washington, D.C. to Norfolk, resulting in the deaths of 48 passengers.
  - Capitol Squirrel Cuts, (WRVA - 441-444); 4 compact discs. Duration: 3 hr., 2 min. 26 sec.
    These recordings are of the WRVA Radio Capitol Squirrel's "provocative thought for the day" segments, which usually were no longer than a five to ten seconds. The Capitol Squirrel made editorial comments on such topics as activities of the General Assembly, litter in the city of Richmond, the city police and bus drivers, drunk driving, and parking in downtown Richmond.
  - Carillon Holiday Programs, 1946-1947, (WRVA - 110-117); 8 compact discs. Duration: 7 hrs., 15 min., 18 sec.
    Carillon holiday programs, 1946-1947, featuring musical selections played on the bells of the Virginia War Memorial Carillon in Richmond by Hilton J. Rufty (1909-1974), to commemorate different holidays, including Easter, Washington's Birthday, Armistice Day, Memorial Day, Thanksgiving, and Christmas.
  - Carl Stutz Show, (WRVA - 97); 1 compact disc. Duration: 19 min., 45 sec.
    Features various musical selections, including "Warsaw Concerto" by Liberace, "I Could Have Danced All Night" from the musical "My Fair Lady," "The Man With a Dream" from the motion picture Seventh Heaven, "Little Star" by Carmen Dragon, and music by the St. Louis Symphony Orchestra. Unknown artists perform "Tojours Moi" and "The Gold and Silver Waltz." Stutz also gives details for a restaurant essay contest, and reads commercial spots for Pepsodent toothpaste, Sanka coffee, Bufferin aspirin, and Westinghouse. The date of this program is unknown.
  - Carl Stutz Show, December 1957, (WRVA - 543-544); 2 compacts discs. Duration: 1 hr., 13 min., 50 sec.
    Consists of recordings of five Carl Stutz Shows. These shows include Carl Stutz hosting the Three Chopt Woman's Club, Bryan Park Woman's Club, Brook Run Junior Woman's Club, Westhampton Junior Woman's Club, Ginter Park Junior Woman's Club at the Alcoa Carefree Home on Westgate Drive in Bon Air, Virginia. Stutz identifies club members, discusses the community service activities in which they are involved, and asks their impression of the home. The Aluminum Company of American (Alcoa) sponsored the building of Alcoa Carefree Homes in twenty-four cities around the United States, including Richmond, Virginia. Designed by Charles M. Goodman (1906-1992) and built by local contractors, these home contained modern amenities and were intended to promote the various uses of aluminum in residential homes. Kayhoe Construction built the Alcoa Carefree Home in Richmond. The house is still standing and is located at 3318 Cedar Grove Road, at the intersection of Cedar Grove Road and Westgate Drive in Bon Air, Virginia.
  - Carter Glass Testimonial, 4 January 1940, (WRVA - 6); 1 compact disc. Duration: 42 min., 49 sec.
    Incomplete recording of a testimonial dinner for Carter Glass held at Sweet Briar College in Sweet Briar, Virginia, on the occasion of his 82nd birthday and the establishment of the Carter Glass professorship of government at the college. Includes speeches by Senator Harry F. Byrd and former Assistant Secretary of the Treasury Russell Cornwell Leffingwell, and Carter Glass, and a performance by the Sweet Briar Glee Club. J. Stewart Bryan, publisher of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, introduces both Byrd and Leffingwell.
  - CBS News, Parts of the World on Segregation, 3 September 1957, (WRVA - 150); 1 compact disc. Duration: 11 min., 34 sec.
    Larry LeSueur reports on the segregation crisis in Little Rock, Arkansas during which Governor Orval Faubus called out the Arkansas National Guard to surround a school to prevent integration. He also reports on the activities of John Casper, a rabid segregationist, in organizing White Citizens' Councils in Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Broadcast includes excerpts from a speech Casper delivered. Finally, LeSueur reports on a news conference with President Eisenhower regarding his feelings on the school desegregation issue. Eisenhower comments that you ""can't change people's hearts by law."
  - Chandler, Alvin Duke, Presidential Inauguration Ceremony, College of William and Mary, 15 May 1953, (WRVA - 294-296); 3 compacts discs. Duration: 2 hr., 46 sec.
    This recording of the inauguration of Alvin Duke Chandler, 22nd president of the College of William and Mary, opens with a 16 minute performance of the William and Mary choir. Speakers include Governor John Stewart Battle, who welcomes visitors and discusses the promises Chandler's leadership will provide the college; and former Governor Colgate W. Darden, who brings greetings from the Virginia colleges. Chandler speaks on the accomplishments, events, and people of the past as they reflect the present and motivate the future of the college. Governor Battle is awarded the honorary Doctor of Laws degree, as is President Dwight D. Eisenhower. Original WRVA recording was titled "President Eisenhower at Williamsburg."
  - Character Promotional Spots, 9 Jan. 1958, (WRVA - 106); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min., 20 min.
    Character promotional spots, 9 January 1958, urging people to listen to WRVA. The spots are voice imitations of famous individuals or fictitious characters, including Winston Churchill, Boris Karloff, Peter Lorre, Jimmy Stewart, Clark Gable, Cary Grant, Elmer Fudd, and Bugs Bunny.
  - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel Dedication, 15 April 1964, (WRVA - 398); 1 compact disc. Duration: 49 min., 41 sec.
    Recording of the dedication and opening of the Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel, including the invocation by Reverend William A. Brown, retired Bishop of the Diocese of Southern Virginia, introductory remarks by Lucious Kellam, chairman of the Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel commission, an address by Governor Albertis S. Harrison, and the release of sea gulls to make the official opening of the bridge-tunnel. Ed Whitehead and Alden Aaroe, WRVA broadcasters, report from the scene, and discuss the potential number of user of the bridge-tunnel and its impact on the economy of Virginia Beach and Virginia's Eastern Shore.
  - Christmas Songs from Virginia's Choirs, December 1960, (WRVA - 378-379); 2 compact discs. Duration: 1 hr., 37 min., 48 sec.
    Contains recordings of Christmas carols sung by the choirs of the College of William and Mary, Richmond Professional Institute, Virginia State College, and Armstrong High School, and by employees of the State Planters Bank assisted by the chancel choir of Beulah Methodist Church of Chesterfield County.
  - Church Across the Way, 1 November 1948, (WRVA - 69); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 3 sec.
    Recording of the 1 November 1948 broadcast of The Church Across the Way, an inspirational program which could be heard each weekday morning from 10-10:30 a.m. This particular program, recorded at the Hotel Richmond Studios of the Edgeworth Broadcasting Service, featured "old fashioned hymn-singing and devotion time" as presented by Sam Workman. Workman also sends on-air greetings for birthdays, anniversaries and shut-ins and promotes his book of poetry, Church Across the Way Book of Poems. Hymns sung on this program include "Do Not Pass Me By" (or "Pass Me Not [Oh Gentle Savior]"); "Face to Face with Christ, My Savior"; "I Gave My Life for Thee"; "Cause Jesus Loves Me"; and "Have Thine Own Way, Lord."
  - Civil War Centennial Opening Ceremonies, Washington and Lee University Chapel, 8 January 1961, (WRVA - 225); 1 compact disc. Duration: 20 min., 10 sec.
    Opening ceremonies, 8 January 1961, of the opening of the Civil War Centennial celebrations in Virginia, which took place at Washington and Lee University Chapel in Lexington. Included are the invocation, and remarks by Congressman William M. Tuck (1896-1983) and Dr. Francis Pendleton Gaines (1892-1963), president emeritus and chancellor of Washington and Lee. Also covered during the ceremonies is the laying of wreaths by representatives from the United Daughters of the Confederacy and the Civil War Centennial Commission.
  - Clements - CBS Feed on World Tonight, [1957], (WRVA - 522); 1 compact disc. Duration: 5 min., 18 sec.
    Includes a CBS News report concerning the United States Supreme Court's refusal to overturn a lower court ruling against Virginia's Pupil Placement Board. The lower court will now presumably order the schools of Newport News and Norfolk to integrate. Jack Clements, WRVA news director, reports on Virginia's reaction to the United States Supreme Court's action and its impact on the current gubernatorial election between J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., a supporter of Massive resistance, and Ted Dalton, a supporter of local option.
  - Clips from Richmond Area Plane Crash Sites, 1959-1961, (WRVA - 414); 1 compact disc. Duration: 2 min., 56 sec.
    Clips of WRVA reports from Richmond area plane crash sites, including the Piedmont Airlines crash near Crozet, Virginia on 30 October 1959, the crash of a Capitol Airlines jet thirty-five miles southeast of Richmond in Charles City County, Virginia near the small town of Holdcroft on 18 January 1960, and the crash of an Imperial Airlines jet two miles southeast of Byrd Field in Richmond on 8 November 1961.
  - College of William and Mary Choir, "Carry Me Back to Old Virginny", (WRVA - 568); 1 compact disc. Duration: 10 min., 43 sec.
    Features an undated performance of the College of William and Mary Choir singing "Carry Me Back to Old Virginny." The performance repeats three times.
  - Colonial Heights Tornado Coverage, 1993, (WRVA - 611); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 35 sec.
    Clips of WRVA's coverage of a tornado that hit Colonial Heights, Virginia on 6 August 1993. Includes the announcement by the station that the tornado had struck the area, as well as clips of reporters on the scene describing the damage to a Wal-Mart store, and to vehicles on the Varina-Enon Bridge. A section of Petersburg was also damaged. There are eyewitness accounts, updates on the traffic situation, and segments from later broadcasts that describe the cleanup and recovery efforts, including interviews with Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) officials. The volume is very low on the majority of the recording.
  - Commemorative Session of the Virginia General Assembly, 29 January 1958, (WRVA - 367); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min., 59 sec.
    Broadcast of a joint meeting of the Virginia General Assembly from the restored Capitol in Williamsburg, Virginia. Includes speeches by Governor J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., and Congressman Howard W. Smith. Almond discusses the development of constitutional government in Virginia and the United States. Smith praises constitutional government and decries the power of the federal judiciary. Both call the demise of constitutional government disturbing.
  - Commemorative Session of the Virginia General Assembly, 1 February 1964, (WRVA - 396); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 29 sec.
    Recording of the commemorative session of the Virginia General Assembly held in the Hall of the House of Burgesses at Colonial Williamsburg. Includes speeches by Governor Albertis S. Harrison and Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. Governor Harrison praises the principles exhibited by the early patriots of Williamsburg. Senator Byrd criticizes the centralization of power and massive spending of the federal government. He refers to the principles of Thomas Jefferson, George Washington, and other early Virginians.
  - Convention Documentary: The Story of John Battle and the 1952 Democratic National Convention, ca. 1952, (WRVA - 30); 1 compact disc. Duration: 55 min., 40 sec.
    Contains sound clips of convention events and news commentary for a documentary produced by WRVA and narrated by George Passage entitled "The Story of John Battle and the 1952 Democratic National Convention." The documentary examines John Battle's role in the fight against the loyalty pledge, which the Virginia delegates believed bound them to support the nominee before he was selected, and the platform before it was adopted. Louisiana, South Carolina, and Virginia refused to support the loyalty pledge and were almost denied participation in the convention. The recordings include excerpts of speeches of Battle, Governor Adlai Stevenson, presidential nominee from Illinois, Senator Richard Russell of Georgia, and the roll call of voting on the resolution. Battle's speech was instrumental in the resolution's defeat. The commentary of George Passage puts the speeches and roll call in context, and provides background information on the events of the convention. The sound clips of the convention events and news commentary are separate. The convention events are the first four tracks and the news commentary are the last two tracks. The news commentary recordings set up each sound clip of the convention events.
  - Corn Cob Pipe Club of Virginia, ca. 1933, (WRVA - 1); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min.
    This recording of the Corn Cob Pipe Club includes music, comedy routines, and a comedic poetry recitation. Also includes information about joining the Corn Cob Pipe Club.
  - Coverage of Miscellaneous News Stories, 1961, (WRVA - 408); 1 compact disc. Duration: 3 min., 56 sec.
    Coverage of miscellaneous news stories from 1961, including a fight and injuries reported in Norfolk, Virginia, a story on State Senator Mills E. Godwin (1914-1999) and organized labor, including the state AFL-CIO, and the smear campaign against his opponent, and a report on Chowning's Tavern at Colonial Williamsburg.
  - Coverage of Public Meeting on Merger Proposal Held in Henrico County, 18 August 1961, (WRVA - 407); 1 compact disc. Duration: 7 min., 36 sec.
    Coverage of a public meeting, 18 August 1961, to discuss the proposed merger of Richmond and Henrico County. John Tansey of WRVA describes the meeting, and numerous recorded clips are also included.
  - Coverage of Standoff at the Hotel John Marshall, 17 October 1973, (WRVA - 595); 1 compact disc. Duration: 49 min.
    Coverage of a standoff at the Hotel John Marshall in Richmond, Virginia between Ralph Carattini and police on 17 October 1973. Carattini, an escapee from the federal prison in Petersburg, took refuge in a room at the hotel, and kept police at bay for four hours. Dave Miller of WRVA reports from the hotel lobby, and also conducts a phone interview with Carattini, hoping to prevent him from committing suicide. Charles Davis narrates from WRVA studios, Larry Matthews reports from outside the hotel, and Howard Bloom reports from a traffic helicopter above the scene. There is coverage of the gun battle that ensued, resulting in Carattini shooting himself, and dying later at MCV Hospital. The recording ends with a summary of events by Larry Matthews in a "Profile" segment.
  - Cullen Johnson: WRVA 30th Anniversary Special, 30 October 1955, (WRVA - 198); 1 compact disc. Duration: 23 min., 38 sec.
    Features E. Cullen Johnson (1913-2001) singing religious and inspirational hymns dedicated by him to various Virginia residents. Charlie Wakefield is featured on piano and organ. Also appearing on the program is Mrs. Henry P. Garber, who sang on WRVA's first broadcast on 2 November 1925.
  - Dalton, Ted, Concession Speech, November 1953, (WRVA - 39); 1 compact disc. Duration: 4 min., 9 sec.
    Ted Dalton, Virginia's Republican candidate for governor in 1953, concedes the election to his opponent, Thomas B. Stanley, the Democratic and Byrd Organization candidate. He congratulates Stanley, and expresses hope that his campaign helped establish a two-party system in Virginia and move Virginia forward in a progressive manner. The last minute of the recording (2:53-4:00) contains a phone interview between George Passage, WRVA news broadcaster, and Harry F. Byrd, Sr., United States senator, concerning Stanley's victory. Byrd answers that he was not surprised by Stanley's victory, but no comment to Passage's other questions. The recording of Byrd is faint and barely audible. The recording also includes a few sound bytes of a radio newsroom in action during an election night.
  - Dalton, Ted, 12 January 1954, (WRVA - 478); 1 compact disc. Duration: 3 min., 16 sec.
    In a statement to the people of Virginia and the members of the Virginia General Assembly, Ted Dalton (1901-1989) calls for people not to regard him as a defeated candidate for Governor. He stresses the importance of teamwork in the upcoming General Assembly session, and emphasizes his support for removal of the poll tax and other electoral reforms, and greater funding for education, the mentally ill, and roads.
  - Dalton, Ted, Concession Speech, November 1957, (WRVA - 523); 1 compact disc. Duration: 1 min., 52 sec.
    Ted Dalton, the defeated Republican candidate for Governor, congratulates J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., on his victory and hopes the contest makes for a better Virginia. He calls for Virginians to look forward not backward when a finding a solution to the great problem of desegregation and still believes the local option plan represents the best means for Virginia to preserve separate public schools.
  - Dalton, Ted, Interview, 1957, (WRVA -105); 1 compact disc. Duration: 5 min., 30 sec.
    Interview, 1957, with Ted Dalton (1901-1989) at his home in Radford, Virginia following his defeat in the Virginia gubernatorial election. Dalton discusses his future plans, his beliefs about what issues dominated the election, especially school integration, and what led to his defeat. He also talks about his views on Virginia's pupil placement plan and massive resistance.
  - Darden, Colgate W., Speech at the Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, Richmond, 9 April 1953, (WRVA - 221); 1 compact disc. Duration: 44 min., 7 sec.
    Speech, 9 April 1953, by Colgate W. Darden (1897-1981) at the Jefferson-Jackson Day dinner in Richmond. Darden begins his remarks with humorous anecdotes. He devotes a large portion of his comments to a comparison of the present political climate with that during the administration of President Andrew Jackson. Darden discusses the dangers of unrestricted majority rule and power, the results of the recent elections, Democratic Party divisions and differences, southern states' representation in Congress and their participation in the Democratic Party, reasons why the Democrats lost in 1952, and what can be done to return the party to a position of prominence.